Eric Fischer

ericmfischer.com

Background

Purpose: I'm a Ph.D. student with a specialization in natural language processing from the Department of Statistics at the University of California, Los Angeles. I perform research on energy-based generative models applied to language at the Center for Vision, Cognition, Learning, and Autonomy at UCLA. My advisors are Dr. Ying Nian Wu and Dr. Song-Chun Zhu.

I earned a Master of Science from the Department of Computer Science at UCLA, submitting a thesis *Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference* (escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw). A deep generative classifier uses Short Run Markov Chain Monte Carlo inference, Langevin dynamics, and backpropagation through time to achieve similar classification accuracy as an analogous discriminative classifier, i.e., a convolutional neural network, while it has the advantages that it can generate data, it can learn unsupervised with additional *unlabeled* data, and it exhibits robustness to adversarial attacks due to the stochasticity of the Langevin equation and the top-down architecture of the underlying generator network.

Research Interests: Natural Language Processing, Representation Learning, Generative Models, Unsupervised Learning, Energy-Based Models, Computer Vision

Education

University of California, Los Angeles | Ph.D. Statistics

Sep 2020 - current

• Specialization: natural language processing

University of California, Los Angeles | M.S. Computer Science

Sep 2018 - June 2020

- Specialization: artificial intelligence
- Thesis: Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference (escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw)

University of California, Los Angeles | B.A. Philosophy

Sep 2009 - June 2013

- Philosophy Departmental Honors, UCLA College Honors, Cum Laude Honors
- Emphasis in philosophy of language and propositional and first-order logic

Publications

Deep Generative Classifier with Short Run Inference | M.S. Thesis | escholarship.org/uc/item/8kx4z8qw

Deep generative classifier uses Short Run Markov Chain Monte Carlo inference, Langevin dynamics, and
backpropagation through time to achieve similar classification accuracy as an analogous discriminative classifier, i.e., a
convolutional neural network, while it has the advantages that it can generate data, it can learn unsupervised with
additional unlabeled data, and it exhibits robustness to adversarial attacks due to the stochasticity of the Langevin
equation and the top-down architecture of the underlying generator network

Learning Multi-Layer Latent Variable Model via Variational Optimization of Short Run MCMC for Approximate Inference | arxiv.org/pdf/1912.01909.pdf | ECCV | contributor (not author)

• Short Run MCMC residual network outperforms a variational autoencoder in terms of image reconstruction error and image synthesis quality, while not requiring the design of a separate inference network

Research

Exact and Cluster Sampling of Ising Model | github.com/EricMFischer/exact-and-cluster-sampling-markov-chains

• A convergence analysis comparing exact sampling, using the Gibbs sampler and coupled Markov chains, to cluster sampling, using the Swendsen-Wang algorithm

First-Order Optimization Methods for CNN | github.com/EricMFischer/first-order-nn-optimization

• Custom Python implementations and convergence analyses of first-order optimization methods Stochastic Gradient Descent (SGD), SGD with momentum, SGD with Nesterov momentum, RMSprop, and Adam

T-Snake Model for Generative Inpainting | github.com/CS269-Capstone/t-snake-mask-generation

• Employs a topology adaptive snake deformable model to probabilistically generate missing image data

Variational Lower Bound Formulation and Application of VAE | github.com/EricMFischer/variational-autoencoder

Statistical formulation and analysis of evidence lower bound for the variational autoencoder, using the MNIST dataset

Experience

Center for Vision, Cognition, Learning, and Autonomy | Graduate Researcher | Los Angeles, CA Dec 2018 - current

• Research on energy-based generative models applied to natural language processing problems

University of California, Los Angeles | Teaching Assistant | Los Angeles, CA

Mar 2020 - current

Have served as a Teaching Assistant and Grader for many undergraduate and graduate statistics courses at UCLA

eXp Realty | South Bay Association of Realtors | Realtor | Los Angeles, CA

Nov 2021 - current

- Realtor for eXp Realty, the fastest-growing real estate brokerage in the world
- Department of Real Estate license ID: 02042145
- Email: eric.fischer@exprealty.com

NatureBox | Full Stack Software Engineer | Redwood City, CA

Mar 2016 - Dec 2017

- Core contributor to new Flux/React web application created after company added direct-to-consumer business
- Led various projects including a payment processor migration, addition of Amazon payments, and a 2nd version of API

Cinemagram | Software Engineer | San Francisco, CA

Sep 2015 - Dec 2015

• Worked with Python, Ruby, and SQL code to construct internal data management interfaces and tools

ClearPath Capital Partners | Wealth Advisor Associate | San Francisco, CA

Sep 2013 - June 2014

• Earned Series 65 (Uniform Investment Adviser Law Exam) license to act as an investment advisor in California

Graduate Coursework

University of California, Los Angeles

STATS 200A - Applied Probability

STATS 200B - Theoretical Statistics (winter 2023)

STATS 200C - High Dimensional Statistics (spring 2023)

STATS 201A - Research Design, Sampling, and Analysis (in progress)

STATS 201B - Statistical Modeling and Learning (winter 2023)

STATS 201C - Advanced Modeling and Inference

STATS 202A - *Statistics Programming* (in progress)

STATS 202B - Matrix Algebra and Optimization

STATS 202C - Monte Carlo Methods for Optimization

COM SCI M276A / STATS M231A - Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning

COM SCI M266A / STATS M232A - Statistical Modeling and Learning in Vision and Cognition (audited)

COM SCI M266B / STATS M232B - Statistical Computing and Inference in Vision and Cognition

COM SCI 247 - Advanced Data Mining

COM SCI 251A - Advanced Computer Architecture

COM SCI 269 - Seminar in Artificial Intelligence: Deformable Models

EC ENGR M235 - Modern Environmental Statistics

EC ENGR 236C - Optimization for Large-Scale Systems

EC ENGR 239AS - Neural Networks and Deep Learning

EC ENGR C243A - Neural Signal Processing (audited, spring 2023)

Independent

Hack Reactor, Advanced Software Engineering Immersive Program, San Francisco, CA, hackreactor.com, June - Sep 2015 CS 224n - Natural Language Processing with Deep Learning, Stanford University on web.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/ CS 230 - Deep Learning, Stanford University on cs230.stanford.edu/class/cs224n/

CS 231n - Deep Learning for Computer Vision, Stanford University on cs231n.stanford.edu

Wrote two chapters and edited several others of two textbooks authored by my Ph.D. advisors Dr. Song-Chun Zhu and Dr. Ying Nian Wu, which summarize over 20 years of artificial intelligence research at UCLA: *Statistical Models for Marr's Paradigm* (ericmfischer.com/publication/book-1/book-1.pdf) and *Stochastic Grammars for Scene Parsing* (ericmfischer.com/publication/book-2/book-2.pdf)